<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: facelink | Tony Lukasavage]]></title>
  <link href="http://tonylukasavage.github.com/blog/categories/facelink/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tonylukasavage.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-24T17:43:15-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://tonylukasavage.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tony Lukasavage]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Away3dLite: Face linking, take 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://tonylukasavage.github.com/blog/2010/06/25/away3dlite--face-linking--take-2/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-25T21:51:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tonylukasavage.github.com/blog/2010/06/25/away3dlite--face-linking--take-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://tonylukasavage.github.com/demos/normals_align/sandbox.html" class="fancybox.iframe"><img title="normals_align" src="http://tonylukasavage.github.com/images/normals2.jpg" alt="" width="433" height="320" /></a></p>


<p>It was great.  I had a moment of triumph.  In my meager 3D and Away3D experience I managed to get face linking functionality into Away3DLite.  Proud of myself, I posted my success at the <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/away3d-dev/browse_thread/thread/960780192fbb77bd" target="_blank">Away3D Dev</a> list.  But my party was soon rained on by one of the Away3D developers, Peter Kapelyan, who immediately informed that my linked objects weren't aligning as they should be.  It felt a lot like that scene in National Lampoon's Christmas Vacation where Clark finally gets the lights lit on his house, only to have his father-in-law inform him that the little lights weren't twinkling...</p></p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><object classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" width="425" height="350" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="src" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/nsaxNehMibg" /><embed type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="425" height="350" src="http://www.youtube.com/v/nsaxNehMibg"></embed></object>

<p style="text-align: left;">I know Peter, thanks for noticing.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">To that end, the above demo is the next revision of my prior face linking code.  This time, I got alignment working.  Because I am 3D math deficient (I'm working on it) I was unable to implement the alignment properly without using a container object for the source and the linked objects.  Someone a little more math savvy can surely make use of the upAxis parameter of the lookAt() function to make it work, but I need some studying before I can do it on my own.  Shawn McInerney from the dev list offered up <a href="http://moosemouse.com/up-object-test.html" target="_blank">a potential solution</a>, but it's a little over my head now.  Perhaps someone else perusing this blog can make use of it.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">I hope Peter didn't take this the wrong way, as I have an abrasive sense of humor that doesn't translate well to written word.  Just in case, <a href="http://www.flashten.com/" target="_blank">here's a link to his site</a> which is extremely clean, cool, slick, and a whole bunch of other adjectives that equal up to awesome.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Away3dLite: Normals and Face Linking]]></title>
    <link href="http://tonylukasavage.github.com/blog/2010/06/23/away3dlite--normals-and-face-linking/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-23T23:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://tonylukasavage.github.com/blog/2010/06/23/away3dlite--normals-and-face-linking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://tonylukasavage.github.com/demos/normals/sandbox.html" class="fancybox.iframe"><img title="normals" src="http://tonylukasavage.github.com/images/normals2.jpg" alt="" width="432" height="323" /></a></p>


<p>The above is a demo of face linking implemented in Away3dLite (right lick to view source).  As you'll see in the demo, face linking allows us to "link" a 3D object to another, rendering it at the center of the source's face and then moving along the face's normal by a given offset.  All credit goes to the original author of the Away3D FaceLink class, as my work was just a minimal modification to port it to Away3DLite.</p>

<p>One thing to note is that this demo required a modification to the Face class, found in away3dlite.core.base.Face.  I simply added a calculated normal and center for the face at creation time and made it available as a public variable.  It's not altogether the cleanest code I've written, but it gives you a good idea of how you might use face linking in your own Away3DLite application.</p>

<p>Just for fun, here's a couple links to other flash apps I've seen that make cool use of faces, vertices, and normals:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.everydayflash.com/blog/index.php/2009/03/16/3d-experiments-with-flash-player-10-and-as3dmod/" target="_blank">EveryDay3D - 3D experiments with Flash Player 10 and AS3Dmod</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.closier.nl/blog/?p=85" target="_blank">Fabrice Closier - Away3D FaceLink</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
